Register of the Bertram David Wolfe papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1914-1976 (Boxes 16-54)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Solomon Schwarz, Labor in the Soviet Union, 1952 October 26; Printed copy (Folder 35: 45)
  - Report on Achmed Mussa Bigi, "I Was Stalin's Bodyguard,", 1953; Typescript (Folder 36: 1)
  - Review in Saturday Review of Max Beloff, Soviet Policy in the Far East, 1953?; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 2)
  - Review of Franz Borkenau, European Communism, 1953?; Typescript (Folder 36: 3)
  - Review of Olaf Caroe, Soviet Empire: The Turks of Central Asia and Stalinism, 1953?; Typescript (Folder 36: 4)
  - Review of W. W. Rostow and Associates, The Dynamics of Soviet Society, 1953?; Typescript (Folder 36: 5)
  - Review in Saturday Review of Leslie C. Stevens, Russian Assignment, 1953?; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 6)
  - Review of Stuart Ramsay Tompkins, The Russian Mind: From Peter the Great through the Enlightenment, 1953?; Typescript (Folder 36: 7)
  - Speech on Soviet succession, 1953; Typescript (Folder 36: 8)
  - "The Rationale of the Purges," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1953 January 14; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 9)
  - "Russian and Soviet Foreign Policy," lecture, Canadian War College, 1953 February 4; Typewritten notes (Folder 36: 10)
  - Review in Saturday Review of William Reswick, I Dreamt Revolution, 1953 February 7 (Folder 36: 11)
  - "Totalitarianism and History," speech, Conference on Totalitarianism, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1953 March; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 12)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, 1953 March 10; Typescript (Folder 36: 13)
  - Review in Saturday Review of Iosif Stalin, Economic Problems of Socialism in the USSR, 1953 April 9; Galley proof. (Folder 36: 14)
  - Review in Saturday Review of Walter Kolarz, Russia and Her Colonies, 1953 April 18; Printed copy (Folder 36: 15)
  - Review in New Leader of Peter Viereck, The Shame and Glory of the Intellectuals, 1953 May 18; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 16)
  - "The Great Blackout: The Total State as a Conspiracy against Its People," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1953 June 4; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 17)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Robert Magidoff, The Kremlin vs. the People, 1953 June 7; Printed copy (Folder 36: 18)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Alexander Orlov, Secret History of Stalin Crimes, 1953 June 7; Printed copy (Folder 36: 19)
  - "The Moral Evil in the Communist Idea," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1953 June 30; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 20)
  - "Memories of Yusuf Meherally," Freedom First, 1953 July; Typescript, mimeograph and printed copy (Folder 36: 21)
  - "The Struggle for the Soviet Succession," Foreign Affairs, 1953 July (Folder 36: 22)
    Mimeograph, printed copy, and Spanish translation.
  - "The Struggle In On," New Leader, 1953 July 20; Mimeograph (Folder 36: 23)
  - Report on Litvinov Papers, 1953 July 22; Mimeograph (Folder 36: 24)
  - "The Kremlin Does Another History," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1953 July 29; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 25)
  - "Meherally, Gandhi and the C.S.P.," Freedom First, 1953 August; Printed copy (Folder 36: 26)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Ernest J. Simmons, ed., Through the Glass of Soviet Literature, 1953 August 9; Printed copy (Folder 36: 27)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Hugh Seton-Watson, From Lenin to Malenkov: The History of World Communism, 1953 September 27; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 28)
  - "An Experiment in Rejuvenation," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1953 October 20; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 29)
  - "Totalitarian Semantics," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1953 November 18; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 30)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Eugene Lyons, Our Secret Allies: The Peoples of Russia, 1953 November 22; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 31)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of I. N. Steinberg, In the Workshop of the Revolution, 1953 December 6; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 32)
  - "The Fate of Statistics in Communist Russia," Socialist International Information, 1953 December 26; Mimeograph (Folder 36: 33)
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, 1953 December 28; Typescript (Folder 36: 34)
  - Report on Alfred G. Meyer, "Marxism: The Unity of Theory and Practice,", 1954?; Typescript (Folder 36: 35)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Claude H. Dewhurst, Close Contact, 1954?; Printed copy (Folder 36: 36)
  - Review of Barrington Moore, Jr., Terror and Progress: USSR, 1954?; Typescript (Folder 36: 37)
  - "The Death of M. N. Roy," Voice of America radio broadcast, 1954 January 26; Mimeographed transcript (Folder 36: 38)
  - "Der Meisterspitzel: Der Abenteuerliche Fall des Roman Malinowski" (The Master Informer: The Strange Case of Roman Malinovskii), Der Monat, 1954 April; Printed copy (Folder 36: 39)
  - Review in Saturday Review of Isaac Deutscher, The Prophet Armed: Trotsky, 1879-1921, 1954 April 17; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 40)
  - Report on Grigorii Kostyuk, "Padenie P.P. Postysheva" (The Fall of P.P. Postyshev), 1954 April 19; Typescript (Folder 36: 41)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Granville Hicks, Where We Came Out, 1954 May 2; Printed copy (Folder 36: 42)
  - "Drowning in a Paper Sea," New Leader, 1954 May 3 (Folder 36: 43)
    Mimeograph, printed copy, and French translation.
  - Review in New York Times of Helen Augur, Zapotec, 1954 May 23; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 36: 44)
  - "The Conversion of a Communist," New Leader, 1954 June 7; Printed copy (Folder 36: 45)
  - "The Strange Case of Diego Rivera," New Leader, 1954 October 11 (Folder 36: 46)
    Printed copy and Spanish translation.
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of N. M. Borodin, One Man in His Time, 1955?; Printed copy (Folder 37: 1)
  - Review of Leonard Schapiro, The Origin of the Communist Autocracy: Political Opposition in the Soviet State, 1955?; Typescript (Folder 37: 2)
  - "A New Look at the Soviet 'New Look,'" Foreign Affairs, 1955 January; Printed copy (Folder 37: 3)
  - Review in Russian Review of C. Grove Haines, ed., The Threat of Soviet Imperialism, 1955 January; Printed copy (Folder 37: 4)
  - "This Business of Peaceful Coexistence," two-part article, New Leader, 1955 January 10 and March 14 (Folder 37: 5)
    Typescript, printed copy, and Italian translation.
  - Review in New York Times of Arthur Voyce, The Moscow Kremlin: Its History, Architecture and Art Treasures, 1955 January 16; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 37: 6)
  - "Coexistence,", 1955 March; Typescript (Folder 37: 7)
  - Review in Commentary of E. H. Carr, A History of Soviet Russia, Vols. I-III: The Bolshevik Revolution, 1917-1923, 1955 March; Printed copy (Folder 37: 8)
  - Review in New York Times of W. W. Kulski, The Soviet Regime: Communism in Practice, 1955 March 6; Printed copy (Folder 37: 9)
  - Review in New York Times of Nikolai Sukhanov, The Russian Revolution, 1917: A Personal Record, 1955 March 9; Typescript (Folder 37: 10)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Nicholas Voinov, The Waif, 1955 March 29; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 37: 11)
  - "Is Co-Existence Possible?," forum with Gerhart Niemeyer, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and Harry Schwartz, Tamiment Institute, New York City, 1955 April 14; Typewritten notes, typescript and printed transcript (Folder 37: 12)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Elizabeth Lermolo, Face of a Victim, 1955 April 15; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 37: 13)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of M. R. Masani, The Communist Party of India, 1955 May 22; Printed copy (Folder 37: 14)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Max Eastman, Reflections on the Failure of Socialism, 1955 June 5; Printed copy (Folder 37: 15)
  - "Adventures in Forged Sovietica: Some True Literary Detective Stories," three-part article, New Leader, 1955 July 25 and August 1 and 8; Printed copy (Folder 37: 16)
  - Speech on Soviet economic growth, Congress on the Future of Freedom, Milan, Italy, 1955 September; Typescript and mimeograph (Folder 37: 17)
  - "The Totalitarian Potentials in the Modern Great-State Society," speech, Congress on the Future of Freedom, Milan, Italy, 1955 September 14; Typescript, and printed copy of excerpts (Folder 37: 18)
  - "'Trapecista' de la Pintura y el Comunismo: Diego Rivera," ('Canvas' of Painting and Communism: Diego Rivera), El Universal, 1955 October 30; Printed copy (Folder 37: 19)
  - Review in New York Times of Salvador de Madariaga, Portrait of Europe, 1955 November 13; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 37: 20)
  - Review in New York Times of Hans Kelsen, The Communist Theory of Law, 1955 November 20; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 37: 21)
  - "The Soviet Slave Labour Reform of 1954-55," Thought, 1955 November 26; Printed copy (Folder 37: 22)
  - "Coexistence and the Cold War," speech, South Orange New Jersey, 1955 December 12; Typewritten notes (Folder 37: 23)
  - Review in American Slavic and East European Review, of Branko Lazitch, Les Partis Communistes d'Europe, 1919-1955 (The Communist Parties of Europe, 1919-1955), 1956?; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 37: 24)
  - Six Keys to the Soviet System (1956)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1961 (Folder 37: 25)
    - Printed copy (Folder 37: 26)
    - Reviews, Printed and typed copies (Folder 38: 1)
    - Translations
      - Bengali, Printed copy (Folder 38: 2)
      - Chinese, Printed copy (Folder 38: 3)
      - German, Printed copy (Folder 38: 4)
      - Japanese, Printed copy (Folder 38: 5)
      - Korean, Printed copy (Folder 38: 6)
      - Portuguese, Printed copy (Folder 38: 7)
      - Urdu, Printed copy (Folder 38: 8)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Ilya Ehrenburg, The Thaw, 1956 January 1; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 39: 1)
  - "The 'New' Soviet Leaders," New Leader, 1956 January 23; Mimeograph and printed copy (Folder 39: 2)
  - Letter to the editor (with others), New York Herald-Tribune, 1956 February 14; Printed copy (Folder 39: 3)
  - Review in Commentary of Leonard Schapiro, The Origin of the Communist Autocracy: Political Opposition in the Soviet State, 1917-1922, and Leopold H. Haimson, The Russian Marxists and the Origins of Bolshevism, 1956 March; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 39: 4)
  - Review in New York Times of G. D. H. Cole, A History of Socialist Thought, Vol. III: The Second International, 1889-1914, 1956 April 29; Printed copy (Folder 39: 5)
  - Letter to the editor, Life, 1956 May 14; Typescript (Folder 39: 6)
  - Review in New Leader of Zbigniew K. Brzezinski, The Permanent Purge, 1956 May 14; Printed copy (Folder 39: 7)
  - Review in Saturday Review of David J. Dallin, The Changing World of Soviet Russia, 1956 May 19; Printed copy (Folder 39: 8)
  - "'War Is the Womb of Revolution': Lenin 'Consults' Hegel," Antioch Review, 1956 Summer; Printed copy (Folder 39: 9)
  - "Stalinism versus Stalin: Exorcising a Stubborn Ghost," Commentary, 1956 June; Mimeograph and printed copy (Folder 39: 10)
  - Review in New York Times of Frederick C. Barghoorn, Soviet Russian Nationalism, 1956 June 17 (Folder 39: 11)
  - "Why Russia Had to Cut Its Armies," New Leader, 1956 June 25; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 39: 12)
  - "Lenin Has Trouble with Engels: A Heretofore Unanalyzed Source of Lenin's Theory of Imperialism," Russian Review, 1956 July; Printed copy (Folder 39: 13)
  - "Stalin's Ghost at the Party Congress," Foreign Affairs, 1956 July (Folder 39: 14)
    Mimeograph, printed copy, and Japanese translation.
  - "The Litvinov 'Diaries': Literary Detective Story," Commentary, 1956 August (Folder 39: 15)
    Galley proof, printed copy, and German translation.
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of George F. Kennan, Soviet-American Relations 1917-1920, Vol. I: Russia Leaves the War, 1956 September 2; Printed copy (Folder 39: 16)
  - Review of Boris Sokoloff, The White Nights: Pages from a Russian Doctor's Notebook, 1956 October 11; Typescript (Folder 39: 17)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of C. L. Sulzberger, The Big Thaw, 1956 November 25; Printed copy (Folder 39: 18)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of B. H. Liddell Hart, ed., The Red Army, 1956 December 9; Printed copy (Folder 39: 19)
  - "Broken Promises,", 1957; Typescript (Folder 39: 20)
  - Khrushchev and Stalin's Ghost (1957)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1970 (Folder 39: 21)
    - Review, Printed and typed copies (Folder 39: 22)
    - Translations
      - Japanese, Printed copy (Folder 39: 23)
      - Spanish, Printed copy (Folder 39: 24)
      - Tamil, Printed copy (Folder 40: 1)
      - Telugu, Printed copy (Folder 40: 2)
  - Review of Isaac Deutscher, Russia in Transition and Other Essays, 1957?; Typescript (Folder 40: 3)
  - Review of Karl A. Wittfogel, Oriental Despotism, 1957?; Typescript (Folder 40: 4)
  - Report on Robert V. Daniels, "The Conscience of the Revolution: The Communist Opposition and the Shaping of Soviet Russia,", 1957 March (Folder 40: 5)
  - "The Communist Party since Stalin," speech, Holyoke University, 1957 April 4; Typewritten notes (Folder 40: 6)
  - "Continuity and Change in the Soviet System," speech, Vassar College, 1957 May 6; Typewritten notes (Folder 40: 7)
  - Review in New Leader of Theodore Draper, The Roots of American Communism, 1957 May 13; Printed copy (Folder 40: 8)
  - "The Hiss Maneuver," National Review, 1957 May 25; Printed copy (Folder 40: 9)
  - "Durability of Despotism in the Soviet System," speech, Conference on Changes in Soviet Society, St. Antony's College, Oxford University, 1957 June 25 (Folder 40: 10)
    Typewritten notes, mimeograph, printed copy, clippings, and French translation.
  - Statement on Soviet power setup for Research Institute on America, 1957 October 30; Typescript (Folder 40: 11)
  - Review in New York Herald Tribune of Gerald Freund, Unholy Alliance: Russian-German Relations from the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk to the Treaty of Berlin, 1957 December 8; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 40: 12)
  - "Marxism Yesterday and Today: The Prophet and His Prophecies," Problems of Communism, 1958 (Folder 40: 13)
    Abstract (printed copy), comments by Herbert Marcuse (typescript), reply by Bertram D. Wolfe (typescript), and correspondence.
  - Review of Merle Fainsod, Smolensk under Soviet Rule, 1958?; Typescript (Folder 40: 14)
  - "Marxism Today," Antioch Review, 1958 Winter; Printed copy (Folder 40: 15)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of George Fischer, Russian Liberalism, 1958 February 25; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 40: 16)
  - Review in New York Herald Tribune of Joseph Scholmer, Vorkuta, 1958 February 27; Printed copy (Folder 40: 17)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of George F. Kennan, Soviet-American Relations, 1917-1920, Vol. II: The Decision to Intervene, 1958 March 9; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 40: 18)
  - Review in New Leader of George F. Kennan, Russia, the Atom and the West, 1958 May 19; Typescript, mimeograph and printed copy (Folder 40: 19)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Baron Petr N. Vrangel', Always with Honor, 1958 June 15; Printed copy (Folder 40: 20)
  - "The Russian Revolution," speech, Conference on Revolutions, Russian Institute, Columbia University, 1958 July 22; Typewritten notes (Folder 40: 21)
  - Review in New York Times of Conrad Brandt, Stalin's Failure in China, 1958 August 28; Typescript (Folder 40: 22)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Boris Pasternak, Doctor Zhivago, 1958 September 7; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 40: 23)
  - "The Soviet Political System," lecture, U.S. Naval War College, Newport, Rhode Island, 1958 October 2 (Folder 40: 24)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Lev Trotskii, Trotsky's Diary in Exile, 1935, 1958 October 19; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 40: 25)
  - "Nationalism and Internationalism in Marx and Engels," American Slavic and East European Review, 1958 December; Printed copy (Folder 40: 26)
  - Comment on Leonard Schapiro, "The Communist Party of the Soviet Union,", 1959?; Typescript (Folder 41: 1)
  - Eulogy of Irakli Tsereteli, 1959; Typescript (Folder 41: 2)
  - "'We Shall Bury You!' A Behind-the-News Profile on Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev,", 1959?; Typescript (Folder 41: 3)
  - "The Deadly Enemy We Face," New Leader, 1959 January 26; Printed copy (Folder 41: 4)
  - Review in Encounter of Lev Trotskii, Trotsky's Diary in Exile, 1935, 1959 March; Typescript, printed copy and clipping (Folder 41: 5)
  - Review in New York Times of E. H. Carr, A History of Soviet Russia, Vol. V, 1959 March 1; Printed copy (Folder 41: 6)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Iosif Stalin, Stalin's Correspondence with Churchill, Attlee, Roosevelt and Truman, 1941-45, 1959 March 1; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 41: 7)
  - Review in New York Times of G. D. H. Cole, A History of Socialist Thought, Vol. IV: Communism and Social Democracy, 1914-1931, 1959 March 8; Printed copy (Folder 41: 8)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Bernard Wolfe, The Great Prince Died, 1959 March 29; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 41: 9)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Robert Strausz-Hupe, William R. Kintner, James E. Dougherty, and Alvin J. Cottrell, Protracted Conflict, 1959 July 19; Printed copy (Folder 41: 10)
  - "Psychological and Philosophical Vulnerabilities of Communism," lecture, U.S. National War College, 1959 July 21 (Folder 41: 11)
    Typewritten notes, printed copy, and Japanese translation.
  - "A Call for National Mourning," advertisement (with other members of the Committee for Freedom for All Peoples), New York Times, 1959 September 14; Printed copy (Folder 41: 12)
  - Review in New York Times of Isaac Deutscher, The Prophet Unarmed: Trotsky, 1921-1929, 1959 September 27; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 41: 13)
  - Review in New York Herald-Tribune of Isaac Don Levine, The Mind of an Assassin, 1959 November 1 (Folder 41: 14)
    Typescript, printed copy, and correspondence, with comments by Isaac Don Levine and reply by Bertram D. Wolfe (printed copies), 22 November 1959.
  - "War and Socialist Internationalism Reconsidered," lecture, Russian Research Center, Harvard University, 1959 December 4; Typewritten notes and printed copy (Folder 41: 15)
  - Report on Julio A. Fernandez, "The Political Elite in Argentina,", 1960s; Typescript (Folder 41: 16)
  - Introduction to John Reed, Ten Days that Shook the World, 1960 (Folder 41: 17)
    Typescript, printed copy, review, and correspondence.
  - Review in Reporter of David Granick, The Red Executive, 1960 March 3; Printed copy (Folder 41: 18)
  - Review in New York Times of E. H. Carr, A History of Soviet Russia, Vol. VI, 1960 April 17; Printed copy (Folder 41: 19)
  - Review in New York Times of Leonard Schapiro, The Communist Party of the Soviet Union, and John S. Reshetar, Jr., A Concise History of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, 1960 May 8; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 41: 20)
  - "Mr. K's Favorite Reporter," New York Times, 1960 June 5; Printed copy (Folder 41: 21)
  - "The New Gospel according to Khrushchev," Foreign Affairs, 1960 July; Offprints (Folder 41: 22)
  - "Two Questions, Mr. Khrushchev!," advertisement (with others), New York Times, 1960 October 7; Printed copy (Folder 41: 23)
  - Review in New York Times of Franco Venturi, Roots of Revolution: A History of the Populist and Socialist Movements in Nineteenth Century Russia, 1960 October 9; Printed copy (Folder 41: 24)
  - Review in New York Times of Robert Vincent Daniels, The Conscience of the Revolution: Communist Opposition in Soviet Russia, 1960 November 20; Printed copy (Folder 41: 25)
  - "Antecedents and Rise of Communism in Russia," lecture, U.S. National War College, Washington, D.C., 1960 December 22; Typescript (Folder 41: 26)
  - Communist Totalitarianism: Keys to the Soviet System, 1961 (1962) (Folder 41: 27)
    Typed and printed copies, correspondence, and reviews.
  - Introduction to Sidney Hook, "Intelligence, Conscience and the Right to Revolution," lecture, University of California, Davis, 1961; Typescript (Folder 41: 28)
  - "Marx, Karl Heinrich," Colliers Encyclopedia, 1961 (Folder 41: 29)
    Typed copy and correspondence.
  - Review in New York Times of David Footman, Civil War in Russia, 1961?; Printed copy (Folder 41: 30)
  - Review of Wladimir S. Woytinsky, Stormy Passage, 1961; Typescript (Folder 41: 31)
  - "Continuity and Change in the Soviet System," speech, Miami, Florida, 1961 April 17; Typewritten notes (Folder 41: 32)
  - "Rosa Luxemburg and V. I. Lenin: The Opposite Poles of Revolutionary Socialism," Antioch Review, 1961 Summer; Printed copy (Folder 41: 33)
  - Review in East Europe of George F. Kennan, Russia and the West under Lenin and Stalin, 1961 June; Mimeograph and printed copy (Folder 41: 34)
  - "Soviet Party Histories from Lenin to Khrushchev," speech, Conference on Soviet Historiography, Institut Universitaire de Hautes Etudes Internationales, Geneva, 1961 July 18; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 41: 35)
  - Review in New York Times of Martin Malia, Alexander Herzen and the Birth of Russian Socialism, 1812-1855, 1961 September 10; Printed copy (Folder 42: 1)
  - "Leon Trotsky as Historian," Slavic Review, 1961 October; Printed copy (Folder 42: 2)
  - "War Comes to Russia-in-Exile," Russian Review, 1961 October; Printed copy (Folder 42: 3)
  - "Nature of the Soviet System," lecture, University of California, Davis, 1961 November 21; Typewritten notes (Folder 42: 4)
  - "Marxism after One Hundred Years," lecture, University of California, Davis, 1961 November 28; Typewritten notes (Folder 42: 5)
  - "Antecedents and Rise of Communism in Russia," lecture, U.S. National War College, Washington, D.C., 1961 December 21; Typescript (Folder 42: 6)
  - "A Century of Marx and Marxism," in Henry L. Plaine ed., Darwin, Marx, and Wagner, 1962 (Folder 42: 7)
    Printed copy and French and Spanish translations.
  - Review in New York Times of Harvey Goldberg, The Life of Jean Jaures, 1962; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 42: 8)
  - Review in New York Times of Nicholas Vakar, The Taproot of Soviet Society, 1962 February 11; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 42: 9)
  - Review in New York Times of Richard Drinnon, Rebel in Paradise: A Biography of Emma Goldman, 1962 February 18; Printed copy (Folder 42: 10)
  - "Reflections on the History of the Comintern," lecture, University of California, Davis, 1962 February 28; Typewritten notes (Folder 42: 11)
  - "Soviet Science: The Case of Lysenko," lecture, University of California, Davis, 1962 March 3; Typewritten notes (Folder 42: 12)
  - "Foreign Policy of Nikita Khrushchev," lecture, Seattle, Washington, 1962 April 23; Typewritten notes (Folder 42: 13)
  - Letter to the editor, Slavic Review, 1962 June; Typescript and printed copy (Folder 42: 14)
  - "Where We Stand," commencement address, Sacramento State College, 1962 June 8 (Folder 42: 15)
    Typescript, printed copy, clipping, and correspondence.
  - "Communist Ideology and Soviet Foreign Policy," Foreign Affairs, 1962 October (Folder 43: 1-2)
  - "Constance du Despotisme Sovietique" (Constancy of Soviet Despotism), Le Contrat Social, 1962 November-December; Printed copy (Folder 43: 3)
  - "Antecedents and Rise of Communism in Russia," lecture, U.S. National War College, Washington, D.C., December 14, 1962. (Folder 43: 4)
    Typewritten notes, typescript, and correspondence.
  - The Fabulous Life of Diego Rivera (1963)
    - General (Folder 43: 5)
      Fragments of typescript, memorandum, press release, and miscellaneous printed matter.
    - Correspondence, 1961-1972 (Folder 43: 6)
    - Reviews, Typed, mimeographed and printed copies (Folder 44: 1-2)